Finding Aid for Roy A. Rappaport Papers 1959-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roy A. Rappaport Papers
1959-1997
Rappaport, Roy A., 1926-1997.
Professor of anthropology at the University of Michigan (1965-1997); chairman of Department of Anthropology (1975-1980); president of American Anthropological Association (1987-1989). Papers include biographical files, correspondence, writings, speeches, lectures, course materials, and files pertaining to various academic programs and environmental projects for which he served as a consultant.
9932 Aa 2
17.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Ann Rappaport in 1999 and 2000 (Donor No. 8810 ).
The collection is open for research except where noted.
Born on March 25, 1926 in New York, New York, Roy Abraham Rappaport obtained a B.S. in Hotel Administration from Cornell University in 1949. He owned and operated Avaloch Inn in Lenox, Massachusetts from 1951 to 1959. Returning to school, he obtained a Ph.D. in Anthropology from Columbia University in 1966, performing field work in Mo'orea, Society Islands and New Guinea. Rappaport joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1965, where he stayed until his death in 1997. Rappaport was chairman of the Department of Anthropology from 1975 to 1980 and president of the American Anthropological Association from 1987 to 1989.
Rappaport's first book, Pigs for the Ancestors, was published in 1968. Based on his ethnographic field work in New Guinea, it established his reputation as an internationally respected scholar. Throughout his career, much of Rappaport's work focused on the study of religion, and more specifically the relationships among religion, society, and ecology. He wrote four books and more than 60 articles, reviews, and book chapters. Rappaport also worked to direct anthropology toward policy issues and he himself consulted on issues related to the social impact of outer continental oil drilling and nuclear waste disposal. His last years were spent working on a book titled Holiness and Humanity, which was published posthumously in 1999.
Known to his friends as "Skip," Rappaport had a generous spirit and was supportive and encouraging to his students and his colleagues. Many of those who knew him considered him brilliant; "the top of your head is better than the inside of most" a colleague once wrote him. At the time of his death from lung cancer in 1997, he was survived by his wife Ann and two daughters, Amelia and Gina.
The Roy A. Rappaport papers provide a glimpse into the active life of an internationally renown and intellectually rigorous anthropologist. Organized into seven series, Biographical Files, Correspondence, Writings, Speeches and Lectures, Classes and Teaching, Consulting, and Topical Files, the papers span the years 1959 to 1997. The strength of the collection is in its documentation of Rappaport's professional and teaching activities. Rappaport's interests in environmental issues, religion, and the application of his knowledge and interests to societal issues are also evident in this collection. The researcher should note that certain aspects of Rappaport's professional career (such as his field work in New Guinea and his time as president of the American Anthropological Association) have a very limited coverage within the collection, in part because field notes and material related to the American Anthropological Association were given to other institutions. Rappaport's field notes are located at the University of California San Diego and his correspondence relating to the American Anthropological Association is at the Smithsonian.
Subjects:
Rappaport, Roy A., 1926-1997.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Yucca Mountain (Nev.); Anthropology--Study and teaching.; Radioactive waste disposal.
- Biographical Files
  The Biographical Files series documents a more personal side of Rappaport's professional life. It contains his yearly review memos for the University of Michigan, which document his professional achievements and personal involvement with various classes and committees at the university. Also of note are transcripts of three interviews conducted with Rappaport towards the end of his life; the interviewers were Sjoerd Jaarsma of the Netherlands, Janet McIntosh, and Tom Fricke. Correspondence and other materials from a 1997 Society for Applied Anthropology tribute session for Rappaport are included here as well, and help to show the influence he had on his colleagues and former students.
  - Curriculum Vitae and Newspaper Articles, circa 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan, 1968; 1974-1996 (Box 1)
  - Interviews with R. Rappaport, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Society for Applied Anthropology Tribute Session, 1997 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains correspondence primarily to and from Rappaport's former students and his colleagues within the Anthropological community. In order to preserve the order of the material as closely as possible to the organizational schemes used by Rappaport, the series has been divided into two subseries: Chronological and Alphabetical. The first subseries has been arranged chronologically by year, and the second has been arranged alphabetically by the individual correspondent's last name. The researcher in search of correspondence between Rappaport and a specific individual should note that it may be necessary to look in both subseries to find the complete record of correspondence. Of particular interest is his correspondence with Derek Freeman, which began shortly after the 1983 publication of Freeman's book Margaret Mead and Samoa: The Making and Unmaking of an Anthropological Myth, which challenged Mead's research and conclusions from her fieldwork in Samoa. As a former student and friend of Mead's, Rappaport defended her work both publicly in articles responding to Freeman's challenges, as well as privately in their correspondence. Rappaport's correspondence with his colleagues from the university's Department of Anthropology (such as Ray Kelly, Norma Diamond, and Aram Yengoyan), as well as his correspondence with his former students (like Ellen Messer and Jan Swearingen), are also rich sources of information about both the internal workings of the department and Rappaport's personal and professional life.
  - Chronological
    - 1963-1966 (Box 1)
    - May 1968-August 1968 (Box 1)
    - August 1968-April 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
    - June 1972-April 6, 1973, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - April 7, 1973-November 1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - March 1973-1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - A-G, 1976; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - H-Z, 1976; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - December 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - July 1981-May 1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
  - Alphabetical
    - Jon Andelson, 1978-1986 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Anthropologists, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous A, 1978-1990 (Box 2)
    - Barbara Babcock, 1974-1984 (Box 2)
    - Paul Bail, 1979 (Box 2)
    - John A. Barnes, 1985-1993 (Box 2)
    - Gregory Bateson, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - Mary Catherine Bateson, 1978-1979; 1987 (Box 2)
    - Frederik Barth, 1978; 1991 (Box 2)
    - Jonathan Bayliss, 1980; 1986 (Box 2)
    - Pete Becker, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Jeremy Beckett, 1978-1987 (Box 2)
    - Aletta Biersack, 1982-1992 (Box 2)
    - Garry Brewer, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Robbins Burling, 1984-1991 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous B, 1978-1995 (Box 2)
    - Bill Christian, 1977-1985 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous C, 1978-1990 (Box 2)
    - Woodrow Denham, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Norma Diamond, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Mary Douglas, 1978-1989 (Box 2)
    - Diane Drigot, 1978 (Box 2)
    - James Duderstadt, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
    - Edgar Dunn, circa 1972 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous D, 1979-1995 (Box 2)
    - Rohn Eloul, 1975; 1983 (Box 2)
    - Tom Ernst, 1969-1984 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous E, 1976-1990 (Box 2)
    - Jay Courtney Fikes, 1983-1994 (Box 2)
    - Judith Fitzpatrick-Nietschmann, 1983-1992 (Box 2)
    - Kent Flannery, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - David Noel Freedman, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - Derek Freeman
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1983-1994; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Regarding The American Scholar, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Cinetal Productions Limited, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - Regarding Scientific American, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - Regarding The Samoa Reader, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Bill Frye, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous F, 1976-1996 (Box 3)
    - Deborah Gewertz, 1979-1990 (Box 3)
    - Maurice Glickman, 1975-1982 (Box 3)
    - Maurice Godelier, 1967-1982 (Box 3)
    - Edie Goldenberg, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Grace Goodell, 1974-1990 (Box 3)
    - Jack Goody, 1981-1992 (Box 3)
    - Roger Green, 1966-1991 (Box 3)
    - James Greenberg, 1975-1994 (Box 3)
    - Richard Grossinger, 1976-1988 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous G, 1980-1996 (Box 3)
    - Susan Harding, 1982-1994 (Box 3)
    - Keith Hart, 1975-1990 (Box 3)
    - William Heaney, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
    - Peter Heywood, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Rob Hide, 1967-1985 (Box 3)
    - Stephen Hugh-Jones, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous H, 1976-1997 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous I, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Carol Jenkins, 1982-1992 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous J, 1971-1996 (Box 3)
    - Bruce Kapferer, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - Miriam Kaprow, circa 1982-1984 (Box 3)
    - Devva Kasnitz, 1975-1979 (Box 3)
    - Ray Kelly, 1982-1986 (Box 3)
    - Everett Kleinjans, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Bruce Knauft, 1982-1988 (Box 3)
    - Conrad Kottak, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Vassili Kryukov, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous K, 1977-1994 (Box 3)
    - Michael Lambek, 1979-1994 (Box 3)
    - Sir Edmund Leach, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Bob Levy, 1978-1989 (Box 3)
    - Edward LiPuma, 1978-1985 (Box 3)
    - Cherry Lowman, 1971-1979 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous L, 1971-1993 (Box 3)
    - Neil McLean, 1985-1989 (Box 3)
    - Bonnie McCay, 1979-1993 (Box 3)
    - Bob McKinley, 1978; 1984 (Box 3)
    - Margaret Mead, 1966-1968; 1978 (Box 3)
    - Robert Meeropol (regarding the Rosenberg case), 1978 (Box 3)
    - Sarah Melzoff, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Ellen Messer, 1978-1992 (Box 3)
    - Rhoda Metraux, 1986-1991 (Box 3)
    - Alexander Militarev, 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - Emilio Moran, 1980-1990 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous M, 1968-1995 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous N, 1977-1993 (Box 3)
    - Sherry Ortner, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous O, 1979-1990 (Box 3)
    - Andrew Pawley, 1988-1992 (Box 3)
    - James Peoples, 1981-1985 (Box 3)
    - Annegret Pollard, circa 1985-1992 (Box 3)
    - Polynesia, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous P, 1976-1993 (Box 3)
    - Frances Svensson Reid, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous R, 1975-1997 (Box 3)
    - Marshall Sahlins, circa 1967 (Box 3)
    - Edward L. Schiefflin, 1970-1988 (Box 3)
    - Robert Segal, 1985-1991 (Box 3)
    - Victor Shnirelman, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
    - Andrew Strathern, 1982-1986 (Box 3)
    - Jan Swearingen, 1978-1991 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous S, 1971-1993 (Box 3)
    - David Thomas, 1977-1986 (Box 3)
    - Valery Tishkov, 1988-1993 (Box 3)
    - Patricia Townsend, 1975-1995 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous T, 1977-1991 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Department of Anthropology, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous V, 1978-1992 (Box 3)
    - Melinda Wagner, 1979-1991 (Box 4)
    - Sidney Waldron, 1971-1995 (Box 4)
    - Peter White, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - Timothy Wilson, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Eric Wolf, 1977-1989 (Box 4)
    - William Wormsley, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous W, 1979-1995 (Box 4)
    - Anatoly Yamskov, 1989-1992 (Box 4)
    - Aram Yengoyan, 1970-1991 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Y and Z, 1986-1992 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1982-1995 (Box 4)
    - Letters of Recommendation, 1968-1995 (Box 18)
      [Restricted]
- Writings
  The Writings series contains two subseries: Columbia and Articles, Papers, and Books. The Columbia subseries includes writings and related materials from the various classes that Rappaport took at Columbia. Of particular interest is the material from a class he took with Margaret Mead in 1960, "Methods and Problems in Anthropology," as it contains the notes and reports from his first field work experiences. The Articles, Papers, and Books subseries contains correspondence between Rappaport and various publishers, as well as reprints of several of the articles. Overall, this series provides good documentation of Rappaport's changing interests.
  - Columbia
    - Comments on the Autonomy of the Superorganic, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Primitive Art-Frazer, 1959 (Box 4)
    - "An African Golden Age", circa 1959-1960 (Box 4)
    - Some Problems in Studying the American Family, circa 1959-1960 (Box 4)
    - Field work and reports for Margaret Mead's course "Methods and Problems in Anthropology", 1960 (Box 4)
    - Typology of Stratified Groups, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Inverted Ethnocentrism-An Aspect of Negro-White Relations in the United States, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Linguistic Analysis of Art, circa 1961 (Box 4)
    - Separate Societies in Polynesia, circa 1961 (Box 4)
    - Related Course Materials
      - Notebooks
        - Anthropology 101, 1959 (Box 4)
        - Anthropology 142 "Minorities", 1959 (Box 4)
        - "Cultures of the Pacific"-Margaret Mead course, 1960 (Box 4)
        - Anthropology 271 "Methods and Problems in Anthropology"-Margaret Mead course, 1960 (Box 4)
        - "Ecology and Organization", 1961 (Box 4)
        - "Cultural Ecology", undated (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
    - Dissertation, circa 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Articles, Papers, and Books
    - "Archaeological Excavations: Mo'orea Society Islands", 1960-circa 1964; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "Aspects of Man's Influence upon Island Ecosystems, circa 1963 (Box 4)
    - "Ecology, Cultural and Non-Cultural", 1965 (Box 4)
    - Pigs for the Ancestors, 1966-1991 (Box 4)
    - Pigs for the Ancestors-Reviews of Epilogue, 1985-1990 (Box 4)
    - "Ritual Regulation of Environmental Relations Among a New Guinea People", 1967; circa 1970; 1994 (Box 4)
    - "Maring Marriage", 1968 (Box 4)
    - "Systems and Sanctity", 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - "Population Dispersal and Land Distribution Among the Maring of New Guinea", 1969 (Box 4)
    - "Sanctity and Adaptation", 1969; 1974 (Box 4)
    - "An Ecological Perspective in Cultural Anthropology", 1969 (Box 4)
    - "The Impact of Technology on the Quality of Life", circa 1960s (Box 4)
    - Bierstedt and Model for Political Analysis, circa 1960s (Box 4)
    - J.S. Mill (political organization), circa 1960s (Box 4)
    - "Ritual as Transducer", circa 1960s (Box 4)
    - "Ecology and Stratification in Polynesia", circa 1960s (Box 4)
    - "Environments and Ecosystems", circa 1960s (Box 4)
    - "Ritual, Sanctity, and Cybernetics", 1971 (Box 5)
    - "Nature, Culture, and Ecological Anthropology", 1971 (Box 5)
    - "The Sacred in Human Evolution", 1971 (Box 5)
    - Rappaport's review of Habitats and Territories by P. Klopfer, 1971 (Box 5)
    - "The Flow of Energy in an Agricultural Society", 1971 (Box 5)
    - Religion Book, circa 1971
      - Chapter 1-Ritual (Box 5)
      - Chapter 2-Sanctity (Box 5)
      - Chapter 3-Religious Experience (Box 5)
    - "Maladaptation" or "Adaptation and Its Structure" by Rappaport, Slobodkin, and Vayda, 1972-1973; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - "Forests and the Purposes of Man", 1972; 1976; 1978 (Box 5)
    - "Energy and the Structure of Adaptation", 1974 (Box 5)
    - "Obvious Aspects of Ritual", 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - "Function, Generality, and Explanatory Power: A Commentary and Response to Bergman's Arguments", 1975 (Box 5)
    - "On Maladaptation", circa 1975 (Box 5)
    - "Adaptation and Maladaptation in Social Systems", 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - "Fertility and Death Among the Maring", 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Ecology, Adaptation and the Ills of Functionalism", 1977; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - "Maladaptation in Social Systems", 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - "Biology, Meaning and the Quality of Life", 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - Ecology, Meaning and Religion, 1979-1982 (Box 5)
    - "Words, Words and the Problems of Language" from The Word: Studies in the Language of Religion and the Religious Meaning of Language, 1979-1989 (Box 5)
    - "Adaptive Structure and Its Disorders", 1970s (Box 5)
    - "Development and Adaptive Structure", circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - Ecology book with Flannery, Kottak, and Ford, circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - "Man is a Poor Dominant", circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - "On Cognized Models", circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - "Postscript on Population", 1970s (Box 5)
    - "Ritual and Sanctity in Communication and Control Systems", circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous writings, 1970s (Box 5)
    - Forward for Conrad Kottak's The Past in the Present: History, Ecology, and Cultural Variation in Highland Madagascar, circa 1980 (Box 5)
    - Reply to James G. Peoples, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Obituary-"Gregory Bateson (1904-1980)", 1982 (Box 5)
    - "Ritual as Communication" in the International Encyclopedia of Communications, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
    - "Desecrating the Holy Woman: Derek Freeman's Attack on Margaret Mead", 1986 (Box 5)
    - Interview with Whole Earth Review, 1988 (Box 5)
    - "Toward Postmodern Risk Analysis", 1988 (Box 5)
    - "Ecosystems, Populations and People", 1990 (Box 5)
    - Forward to Nancy Howell's Surviving Fieldwork, 1990 (Box 5)
    - "Ritual, Time, and Eternity", 1991 (Box 5)
    - "Appendix B-The Human Environment" from Assessment of the U.S. Outer Continental Shelf Environment Studies Program, 1992 (Box 5)
    - "Veracity, Verity and Verum in Liturgy", 1993 (Box 5)
    - "The Anthropology of Trouble", 1993 (Box 5)
    - Rappaport's comments in "Cultural Anthropology's Future Agenda" by Robert Borofsky, 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Humanity's Evolution and Anthropology's Future", 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Disorders of Our Own: A Conclusion", 1994 (Box 6)
    - "On the Evolution of Morality and Religion: A Response to Lee Cronk", 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Considering the Meaning of Human Environment and the Nature of Impact", 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Logos, Liturgy, and the Evolution of Humanity", 1995 (Box 6)
    - Review of Adam Kuper's The Chosen Primate: Human Nature and Cultural Diversity, 1995 (Box 6)
    - "Law, Meaning and Holism, 1995 (Box 6)
    - A comment on John Bennett, 1996 (Box 6)
    - "Risk and the Human Environment, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Forward to Global Ecosystems: Creating Options Through Anthropological Perspectives, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Holiness and Humanity, 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - "Comments on Kai Lee's Statement on Social Science Elements of Environmental Research", circa 1990s (Box 6)
    - "Morality, Moralism and Reducing the Frequency of Abortion", circa 1990s (Box 6)
    - Evaluations of Other People's Manuscripts for Various Publishers, 1976-1994 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence with Publishers, 1966-1997; 2 folders (Box 6)
- Speeches and Lectures
  The Speeches and Lectures series contains many of the professional speeches and lectures given by Rappaport at various conferences, symposia, and colloquia, and also includes some correspondence. The material in the series reflects his professional involvement with various individuals and organizations.
  - 10th Pacific Science Congress-UNESCO Symposium on Man's Place in the Island Ecosystem-"Island Cultures", 1961 (Box 6)
  - "Ritual Regulation of the Environmental Relations of the Tsembaga"-Detroit, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Evolution of Ecological Systems Seminar-Columbia University-"Ritual Regulation of Environmental Relations in New Guinea", 1965 (Box 6)
  - AAA Meeting in Washington-"The Place of Pigs in the Diet, Ecology and Politics of a New Guinea People", 1966 (Box 6)
  - Ottawa Paper, Discussion, and Summary-"Population Dispersal and Land Distribution Among the Maring of New Guinea", 1967 (Box 6)
  - East-West Center (Hawaii)-International Honors Program Seminar-"Man and His Environment", 1968 (Box 6)
  - "Ritual and Sanctity in Communication and Control", 1968 (Box 6)
  - Chicago Paper-Generalizations on "Ritual Regulation of Environmental Relations in New Guinea", circa 1968 (Box 6)
  - Symposium on Social Structure in Highland New Guinea and the Island Pacific, 1969 (Box 6)
  - National Science Teachers Association-"Purpose, Property and Environmental Disaster", 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - Burg Wartenstein Symposium-The Moral and Esthetic Structure of Human Adaptation-"Sanctity and Adaptation", 1969 (Box 6)
  - Columbia University Seminar-"Ritual, Sanctity and Ecological Systems", 1969 (Box 6)
  - Ecology of Complex Society Symposium, circa 1960s (Box 6)
  - ENACT (University of Michigan)-"Religious Aspects of the Ecological Movement", 1970 (Box 6)
  - Wenner-Gren Symposium-"Restructuring the Ecology of Cities", 1970 (Box 6)
  - Center for Ecological Development, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - "Levi-Strauss in the Swiddens", circa 1970 (Box 6)
  - M.C. Interns (Ecology), 1971 (Box 6)
  - Wayne State and University of London-Maladaptation, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Burg Wartenstein Symposium-Ritual: Reconciliation in Change-"Ritual as Communication and as State", 1973 (Box 6)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science-"Energy and the Structure of Adaptation", 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Cumberland Lodge-Symposium on Lying and Deceit-"Liturgies and Lies", 1974 (Box 6)
  - American Anthropological Association-Symposium on The Work of Ritual: Time, Motion and Emotion-"On the Structure of Ritual", 1975 (Box 6)
  - Stafs Talk-Maladaptation, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Oregon State-Energy and the American Dream Forum-"Energy and Adaptive Structure in Social Systems", 1976-1977 (Box 6)
  - Society for the Study of Human Biology (Oxford)-Symposium on Human Behavior and Adaptation-"Adaptation and the Structure of Ritual", 1976-1978 (Box 6)
  - Alaska Anthropological Association-Keynote Address-"Adaptation and the Structure of Ritual", 1977; 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - American Sociological Association-"Biology, Meaning and the Quality of Life", 1977 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan-Conference on Narcissism in Modern Society-"Remarks on Narcissism in Contemporary Religion: Comments on Pruyser", 1977 (Box 6)
  - Rene Dubos Forums on Energy, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Central States Anthropological Society-Discussant for the Symposium on Environment and Awareness: Anthropological Approaches, 1978 (Box 7)
  - "On Reflexivity and Ritual", 1978-1980 (Box 7)
  - The Institute on Man and Science-Workshop on the Social Impacts of Decentralization-"Decentralization", 1978 (Box 7)
  - National Research Council-Panel on Human Ecology in the Tropics, 1978-1979 (Box 7)
  - Texas-"On Cognized Models" and "Adaptive Structure and Its Disorders", circa April 24, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Michigan State-"Feast Cycles as Liturgical Orders", 1979 (Box 7)
  - Chautauqua Futures Week-"Sanctity and Change", 1979 (Box 7)
  - Comments for Symposium on Materialist Models of Mental Culture-"Ecology and Semiotics: Toward and Integrated Approach", circa 1970s (Box 7)
  - Lecture on Justice Brandeis, circa 1970s (Box 7)
  - New York Academy of Sciences-Pigs for the Ancestors in Retrospect-"On Pigs for the Ancestors", April 28, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Oak Ridge National Laboratory, September 15, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Talk to Michigan Energy Group-"Energy and Adaptive Structure in Social Systems", February 2, 1981 (Box 7)
  - American Anthropological Society annual meeting-Discussion of Papers in Honor of Mervyn Meggitt, December 5, 1982 (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan-Collegiate Institute for Values and Science (CIVS)-Values in Anthropology, March 31, 1983 (Box 7)